<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<!--

Copyright 2007 Steve R. Hastings (steve@hastings.org)

-->
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1//EN" "file:///usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.1/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry>
  <refentryinfo>
    <address>
      <email>lf@langri.com</email>
    </address>
    <author>
      <firstname>Steve</firstname>
      <surname>Hastings</surname>
    </author>
    <date>2007-07-19</date>
  </refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>lf</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>lf</refname>
    <refpurpose>list files, sorted by extensions, in a terse format</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>lf</command>
      <arg><replaceable>OPTION</replaceable>...</arg> <arg><replaceable>FILE</replaceable>...
      </arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
  <refsect1>
    <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    <para><command>lf</command> is a command-line tool for listing files, similar in some ways to <command>ls(1)</command>.  <command>lf</command> sorts the filenames by extension, and displays them in a terse output format.  Here is an example:</para>
<programlisting>
DIRS: bak junk
    : apples filelist.md5sum makefile README
   c: bar baz foo
   o: baz foo
 txt: readme
</programlisting>
<para>
Directory names are shown first, marked by the string
"<computeroutput>DIRS</computeroutput>"; directories
with extensions are not treated specially.  If any files with no extension
are present they will be listed next, followed by any files that do have
extensions.  In each case the extension is printed, followed by a list
of filenames with the extension removed.
</para>
<para>
Some extensions are ignored.  Filenames with extensions that are too
long (default: longer than 4 characters) are treated as if there were no
extension in the filename.  In the example above, filelist.md5sum fell
under this rule and was put on the line for files with no extension.
</para>
<para>
If you specify no filename arguments, <command>lf</command> will list the files in the
current directory.  If you specify one filename argument, <command>lf</command> will list
it; if it is a directory, <command>lf</command> will list the files contained in that
directory.
</para>
<para>
If you specify multiple filename arguments and some of them are
directories, <command>lf</command> will list the contents of the directories.  Here is an
example: suppose you had two directories, foo and bar, and they had some
files in them.  This is the result if you run <userinput>lf foo bar</userinput>:
</para>
<programlisting>
    : bar/notes foo/README
   c: bar/foocode foo/barcode
   h: bar/foocode foo/barcode
</programlisting>
<para>
If you instead called <command>lf</command> with the --directory (-d) argument, the
contents of directories would not be read.  You would get a result like
this:
</para>
<programlisting>
DIRS: bar foo
</programlisting>
<para>
<command>lf</command> treats files of the format "foo-1.23" specially.  Files with names
like this don't really have a sensible extension, and it's better to
have them listed with the no-extension files.  When any filename
contains a dash ('-'), followed by zero or more digits, followed by a
period ('.'), followed by one or more digits, <command>lf</command>
treats the filename as if it had no extension.
</para>
<para>
The extensions are printed in sorted order, and the filenames are
sorted as well within each line.
</para>
<para>
If any files have a dot as the last character of their filename, <command>lf</command> will
consider their extension to be "." (a single dot).  Other than this
special case, <command>lf</command> prints file extensions without a dot.
</para>
<para>
<command>lf</command> tries to get the user's default locale, and use locale-specific
functions for sorting filenames.  (If <command>lf</command> is called with the
--force-lower-case option, the user's default locale is used for the
lower-case function too.)  If <command>lf</command> is unable to get the locale, it will
fall back to the "C" locale which is based on plain ASCII.
</para>
<para>
Removing the extensions from the filenames saves some space, and you can fit
quite a bit of information into one screen.  Also, it can be valuable
to see your files sorted by extension; you can quickly tell what kinds
of files are in the directory.
</para>
<para>
Like <command>ls(1)</command>, if invoked with no
filenames specified as arguments, <command>lf</command>
will list the files
in the current directory.
</para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>OPTIONS</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>--license</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--licence</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Show the text of the free software license under which <command>lf</command> is
distributed.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-a</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--show-all</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Include files that would normally be hidden.  On Linux and *NIX file
systems, filenames that start with a period ('.') would normally be hidden.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-A</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--ascii</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Sort by ASCII values of characters in filenames rather than the default
locale.  Case-sensitive.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-I</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--ascii-ic</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Sort by ASCII values of characters in filenames rather than the default
locale.  Case-insensitive.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-L</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--locale</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Sort according to the default locale.  This is <command><command>lf</command></command>'s
default behavior.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-d</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--directory</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Print directory names as if they were filenames, rather than listing
their files.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-X &lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--ext-spacing=&lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Sets the width reserved on each line for the extension.  Extensions
shorter than this are right-justified within this width.  The default
value is 4.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-Z &lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--ext-width-limit=&lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Sets the limit on how long an extension can be.  Any extension longer
than this limit is ignored (the filename is treated as if it did not
contain any extension).  The default value is 4.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-F</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--force-lower-case</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Forces all filenames (including directory names) to lower case.  This
is mainly useful if you are dealing with a file system that only
contains upper-case filenames, such as an old FAT file system.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-N &lt;string&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--name-separator=&lt;string&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Specify a different separator to print between base filenames.  The
default separator is a single space.  You could, for example, set
the separator to a comma and a space (", ") if you have many
filenames with spaces in them and you want to make it easier to tell
where the files actually end.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-S &lt;string&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--replace-spaces=&lt;string&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Specifies a string that will replace spaces in filenames in the
listing.  You could, for example, set this to '*' and then the filename
"<computeroutput>this is my file</computeroutput>"
would print as
"<computeroutput>this*is*my*file</computeroutput>".
(Note that the shell expands a '*' so you will need to quote it.)
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-w &lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--line-width=&lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Format output in lines of this many characters or fewer.  The default
value is 80.  <command>lf</command> will start a new line of output if printing a filename would make the line longer than this limit.
</para>
<para>
In a graphical desktop environent the available width of lines in a
terminal emulator can change if the window is resized.  The
<command>bash(1)</command>
shell has a shell variable, COLUMNS, that always contains the current
line width.  With the command "export COLUMNS" you can make it into an
environment variable, and <command>lf</command> will be able to retrieve its value.  You
could then set the LFOPTS environment variable to include
"--line-width=$COLUMNS", and when you resize the width of your terminal
emulator, <command>lf</command> will print listings that fit perfectly in the new width of
the terminal emulator.  If you do this, you can use the --margin (-M)
option to keep filenames from going all the way to the end of the line.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-M &lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--margin=&lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Reserve (leave blank) this many spaces on the right side of each line.  The
default value is 0, so by default <command>lf</command> will print filenames all the way
to the full line width.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-v &lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--verbose=&lt;number&gt;</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
<para>
Control how verbose the output is.  Currently three levels are defined:
<simplelist>
<member>
0: just print filenames.
</member>
<member>
1: print a header showing directory being listed, then print filenames.
</member>
<member>
2: print a report on how options are set, then print the same output as level 1.
</member>
</simplelist>
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <option>-V</option>
        </term>
        <term>
          <option>--version</option>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Show version information.  Complies with GNU standard --version format.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/lf1/">SourceForge project for lf</ulink>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>ENVIRONMENT VARIABLES</title>
    <para>
If you set a variable called LFOPTS in the environment, lf will
parse it for options.  These will be treated the same as if they had
been typed as command-line arguments to lf.  If an option is set in
LFOPTS and set a different way from the command-line, the command-line
argument will override the argument in LFOPTS.
</para>
<para>
For example, if you often work with extensions 5 characters long, you
might want to set LFOPTS like so:
</para>
<para>
export LFOPTS="--ext-spacing=5 --ext-width-limit=5"
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>HISTORY</title>
    <para>
In the 1980's I used a freeware program for MS-DOS called LF.COM,
which listed files sorted by extension, and which gave me the idea for
this program.  The author of LF.COM was not listed in the program
anywhere, nor was source code available.  Whoever wrote LF.COM: thank
you!
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>AUTHOR</title>
    <para>
Written by Steve R. Hastings.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>REPORTING BUGS</title>
    <para>
	Report bugs to: lf@langri.com
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>COPYRIGHT</title>
    <para>
	Copyright © 2007 Steve R. Hastings.
    </para>
    <para>
	This is free software; see the source code for copying conditions.  There is
	NO  warranty;  not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
	PURPOSE.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1>
    <title>BUGS</title>
    <para>
If you use the --force-lower-case (-F) option when running lf on a file
system that allows mixed-case filenames, and there are two filenames
that differ only by case, lf will silently show only one name for both.
In other words, if both names are identical when forced to lower-case,
lf will treat them as a single file.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
